Michele Piazzai

Carlos III University of Madrid Department of Business Administration

Calle Madrid 126, 28903 Getafe, ES
 Normante 6.0.23
 +34 916 24 9322
 michele.piazzai@uc3m.es
 https://piazzai.github.io

ORCID: 0000-0001-9676-7422 Web of Science: ABH-6674-2020 Scopus: 56123810600

SHORT BIO _

I am a social scientist interested in organization, strategy, and decision-making, especially in the context of creative industries. In my research, I apply statistical and computational methods to explain how people use concepts and categories to make sense of products, and how product categories, in turn, shape firms' competitive behavior.

ACADEMIC POSITIONS

•	Assistant Professor of Management, Carlos III University of Madrid	2020-2024
•	Assistant Professor of Innovation, University of Amsterdam	2017-2020

EDUCATION

EDOCATION		
Data Science Specialization, Utrecht University	2018	
PhD cum laude, Applied Logic, Delft University of Technology	2018	
Medici Summer School, University of Bologna	2015	
Exchange, The Chinese University of Hong Kong	2012	
MA cum laude, Cultural Economics, Erasmus University Rotterdam	2012	
BA summa cum laude, Humanities, Sierra Nevada College	2011	

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS _

- Michele Piazzai, Min Liu, and Martina Montauti (2024). Cognitive economy and product categorization. *Organization Science*. https://doi.org/10.1287/orsc.2021.15751
- Michele Piazzai and Nachoem Wijnberg (2019). Product proliferation, complexity, and deterrence to imitation in differentiated-product oligopolies. *Strategic Management Journal* 40(6), 945–958. https://doi.org/10.1002/smj.3002

OTHER PUBLICATIONS _

- Angelo Tomaselli, Oguz Acar, Michele Piazzai, and Nachoem Wijnberg (2024). When
 more is more. *California Management Review Insights*. https://cmr.berkeley.edu/2024/
 04/when-more-is-more
- Michele Piazzai and Marilena Vecco (2020). Deaccessioning. *Oxford Bibliographies in Anthropology*. https://doi.org/10.1093/obo/9780199766567-0246
- Min Liu, Martina Montauti, and Michele Piazzai (2018). Old at heart, young at the periphery: An age-dependence approach to resource partitioning. *Academy of Management Best Papers Proceedings* 2018(1), 11589. https://doi.org/10.5465/AMBPP.2018.31
- Marilena Vecco, Andrej Srakar, and Michele Piazzai (2017). Visitor attitudes toward deaccessioning in Italian public museums: An econometric analysis. *Poetics* 63, 33–46. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.poetic.2017.05.001
- Willem Conradie, Sabine Frittella, Alessandra Palmigiano, Michele Piazzai, Apostolos Tzimoulis, and Nachoem Wijnberg (2017). Toward an epistemic-logical theory of categorization. *Theoretical Aspects of Rationality and Knowledge*. EPTCS 251, 167–186 (Open Publishing Association). https://doi.org/10.4204/eptcs.251.12

- Michele Piazzai and Nachoem Wijnberg (2017). Diversification, proliferation, and firm performance in the US music industry. **Academy of Management Best Papers Proceedings** 2017(1), 16528. https://doi.org/10.5465/AMBPP.2017.29
- Willem Conradie, Sabine Frittella, Alessandra Palmigiano, Michele Piazzai, Apostolos Tzimoulis, and Nachoem Wijnberg (2016). Categories: How I learned to stop worrying and love two sorts. *Logic, Language, Information, and Computation*. LNCS 9803, 145–164 (Springer). https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-662-52921-8_10
- Marilena Vecco and Michele Piazzai (2015). Deaccessioning of museum collections: What do we know and where do we stand in Europe? *Journal of Cultural Heritage* 16(2), 221–227. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.culher.2014.03.007

COURSES TAUGHT	
Carlos III University of Madrid	
Organizational Design (coordinator), BScStrategic Management, PhD	2020–2024 2020–2022
University of Amsterdam	
 Thesis Proposal Workshop (coordinator), BSc/MSc Innovation Management (coordinator), BSc Cases in Creative Entrepreneurship, MSc Cultural Entrepreneurship and Innovation, MSc Strategic Management and Marketing in the Creative Industries, MSc 	2019–2020 2018–2020 2017–2019 2015–2019 2015–2017
Delft University of Technology	
 Formal Methods for Strategic Decision-making (TA), BSc Integration Economics, Law, Philosophy, and Technology (TA), BSc Ethics and Engineering (TA), MSc 	2016–2017 2015–2016 2014–2017
INVITED SEMINARS	
 Strategy Group, University of Edinburgh Department of Logic, History, and Philosophy of Science, UNED Madrid Strategy and International Business Group, University of Warwick Department of Business Administration, Carlos III University of Madrid Strategy and Entrepreneurship Group, NOVA University of Lisbon Strategy Group, IE University School of Business, Maynooth University Department of Mathematics and Computer Science, Chapman University Cultural Sociology Group, University of Amsterdam Management and Marketing Group, Durham University Entrepreneurship and Innovation Section, University of Amsterdam 	2024 2023 2020 2019 2019 2019 2019 2018 2017 2017
CONFERENCES AND WORKSHOPS	
 EGOS Colloquium, University of Milano-Bicocca Nagymaros Conference, University of Amsterdam Nagymaros Conference, Zoom Nagymaros Conference, Zoom Nagymaros Conference, Stanford University AOM Annual Meeting, Boston Nagymaros Conference, University of Cambridge Applied Logic Workshop, Delft University of Technology SMS International Conference, Houston AOM Annual Meeting, Atlanta 	2024 2023 2021 2020 2019 2018 2018 2017 2017

 Nagymaros Conference, Carlos III University of Madrid Creative Industries Research Seminar, Free University Amsterdam Logic and Algebra Workshop, University of Johannesburg International Workshop on Logic and Cognition, Sun Yat-sen University AOM Annual Meeting, Anaheim EGOS Colloquium, Federico II University of Naples Lorentz Workshop, Leiden University Logic and Algebra Workshop, University of Johannesburg Logic and Algebra Workshop, University of Johannesburg EGOS Colloquium, American College of Greece EGOS Colloquium, Erasmus University Rotterdam IASPM Conference, Erasmus University Rotterdam Music Matters Masterclass, Tilburg University 	2017 2017 2017 2016 2016 2016 2016 2015 2015 2014 2014 2014
RESEARCH VISITS	
 Department of Economics and Business, Pompeu Fabra University Department of Mathematics and Computer Science, Chapman University Department of Pure and Applied Mathematics, University of Johannesburg Graduate School of Business, Stanford University Department of Pure and Applied Mathematics, University of Johannesburg Department of Pure and Applied Mathematics, University of Johannesburg Department of Arts and Culture Studies, Erasmus University Rotterdam 	2016 2016
AWARDS AND GRANTS	
 UC3M Business Teaching Award, Carlos III University of Madrid UC3M Business Teaching Award, Carlos III University of Madrid UC3M Business Teaching Award, Carlos III University of Madrid Ramón y Cajal Fellowship, Spanish Ministry of Science Knowledge Generation Project (co-applicant), Spanish Ministry of Science Departmental Scholar Award, Sierra Nevada College Undergraduate scholarship, Sierra Nevada College Undergraduate scholarship, National Italian American Foundation 	2023 2022 2021 2021 2020 2011 2010 2009
SERVICE	
Departmental activities	
 Strategic Funding Group, Carlos III University of Madrid Business Administration Program Committee, University of Amsterdam 	2023–2024 2018–2019
Conference organization	
Co-organizer, Nagymaros ConferenceScientific Committee, Nagymaros ConferenceOrganizer, Applied Logic Workshop	2024 2020 2018
Societies	
Webmaster, Nagymaros Group	2023-2024
Peer reviews	
 AOM Annual Meeting (3) Management Science (1) Organization Science (2) Organization Studies (1) Strategy Science (1) 	

OPEN-SOURCE PROJECTS

- hacked-jekyll, https://rubygems.org/gems/hacked-jekyll
- jekyll-nagymaros, https://rubygems.org/gems/jekyll-nagymaros
- opencolor, https://ctan.org/pkg/opencolor
- uvaletter, https://ctan.org/pkg/uvaletter
- arguelles, https://ctan.org/pkg/beamertheme-arguelles
- cvless, https://rubygems.org/gems/cvless

LANGUAGES _

• Natural: Italian, English, Spanish

• Scripting: Bash, Python

Web: HTML, CSS, JavaScriptData: R, Stata, SQL, VBA

• Typesetting: LATEX